A Guide to the Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10320-d
Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Papers ca. 1925-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10320-d
3100 items
Harry F. Byrd, Jr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers is controlled by the Honorable Harry F. Byrd, Jr. An applicant for access who is not associated with the University of Virginia must furnish to the Director of Special Collections a brief description of his academic or other qualifications, a summary of his research project, and a description of any projected publication that might make use of material from, or material derived from, the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers. The Director of Special Collections will contact Senator Byrd and will notify the applicant of the Senator's decision.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library on February 12, 1996, by Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Winchester, Virginia.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., of Winchester, Virginia, contains ca. 3,100 items, (10 Hollinger boxes, one oversize folder, and 83 bound volumes, ca. 19 linear shelf feet) ca. 1925-1989, consisting chiefly of bound scrapbooks, bound copies of speeches and press releases, and Congressional Record speeches and inserts, documenting his life and career during his service in the U.S. Senate, 1965-1982; news clippings; a folder of material concerning the Winchester Junior Board of Trade; a report on the "Study of the Organization of the State Government of Virginia" (1947 Dec 29); and personal and professional correspondence during his eighteen years in the Virginia Senate.
There is also one folder of correspondence between Harry F. Byrd, Jr., managing editor of the Winchester Star from 1933-1946, with Ralph Fansler, about the running of the paper while Byrd was in active service in the Navy during World War II. "Special letters" have also been kept separate by Harry F. Byrd, Jr. in an individual folder (for list of notable correspondents, see folder listing).
Also present is material pertaining to Harry F. Byrd, Sr, including a scrapbook; business papers, chiefly concerned with the apple orchards; correspondence (for list of notable correspondents, see folder listing); correspondence concerning his re-election to the Senate in 1952; photographs; genealogy; news clippings; a copy of Time magazine featuring Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. on the cover; political papers, including a vote tally for the Shenandoah Valleyin Senator Byrd's own handwriting in the race for governor in 1925 and the expenses and receipts for his last campaign (for both of these items, see Harry F. Byrd, Jr.'s letter in the front of the folder); and speeches.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence of Harry F. Byrd, Jr. in the Virginia Senate
  - Correspondence A-C, including: Harvey B. Apperson (Attorney General - VA); Harry F. Byrd, Sr.; Admiral Richard E. Byrd; & Mrs. Richard E. Byrd, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Branch Banking, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Chiropractor Bill, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence D-G, including: Ralph Fansler; & Freeman Gosden, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Finance, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence H-K, including: Rep. Burr P. Harrison; Dowell J. Howard; & Jack Kilpatrick, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Insecticide, Fungicide, & Rodenticide, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence L-P, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - New Market Charter Bill, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - President Terms of Office, 1948 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence R-S, including: A. Willis Robertson, 1948 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Roads, 1948 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Schools, including: Robert Whitehead, 1948 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence T-Z, 1948 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - United Nations, including: Rep. Burr P. Harrison, 1948 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence A-B, including: John S. Battle; Admiral Richard E. Byrd; (to) J. Lindsay Almond; & Watkins M. Abbitt, 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence C-F, including: Ralph Fansler; James W. Fletcher (welfare lists); & Senator J. Allen Frear, Jr., 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence G-K, including: (to) Judge Hamilton Haas; Dowell J. Howard, 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence L-R, including: Harry T. Phoebus; Lewis F. Powell, Jr.; & Walter E. Rogers, 1950 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Medical Education, 1950 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence S-V, including: Louis Spilman; James G. Stahlman, Nashville Banner; & Governor William M. Tuck, 1950 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence W-Z, including: David McCord Wright, 1950 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence A-C, 1954 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence D-I, including: Colgate W. Darden, Jr., 1954 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence J-R, 1954 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence S-Z, 1954 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence A-G, including: Watkins M. Abbitt & (to) J. Lindsay Almond, 1956 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence H-O, including: Burr P. Harrison & "Integration & Teachers", 1956 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence P-Z, including: A. Willis Robertson, J. Kenneth Robinson, & Harry C. Stuart, 1956 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence A-G, 1958 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence H-O, 1958 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence P-Z, including: Herman E. Talmadge & A. Willis Robertson, 1958 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence A-C, 1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence D-G, including: Thomas N. Downing, 1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence H-L, 1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence M-R, 1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence S-Z, including: William M. Tuck, 1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence A-B, including: Senator Gordon Allott & Frank Bane, 1962 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence C-D, including: A.D. Chandler & Lyman C. Harrell, Jr. (see A.B. Clements), 1962 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence E-K, including: Burr P. Harrison, 1962 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence L-M, including: "liquor-by-the-drink" letters & John O. Marsh, Jr., 1962 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence N-R, 1962 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence S-Z, including: Tom Frost & William M. Tuck, 1962 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence A-C, 1964 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence D-H, 1964 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence J-P, including: Lewis Powell & Fred G. Pollard, 1964 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence - McMurran House Bill #832, 1964 Feb; (2 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence - Motor Vehicle Titling Tax, 1964 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence R-Z, 1964 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence - School Tuition Grants Bill, 1964 (Box Box 7)
- Series II: Byrd Family Papers
  - Business Papers, 1943-1960 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence of Harry F. Byrd, Jr. and Ralph Fansler, 1942-1944 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., including: Ella W. Flood (1874 Jan 5); Richard Evelyn Byrd (1925 Aug 19); A. Willis Robertson (1947 Sep 10); Ted Dalton (1948 Nov 21); Earl L. Butz (1956 Jan 9); Dwight D. Eisenhower(1956 Feb 15, 29; Nov 8; 1959 Oct 5; 1960 Aug 29 & Oct 28); Lyndon B. Johnson (1956 Aug 31); N.F. Twining, U.S.A.F. (1956 Sep 13); George M. Humphrey (1956 Sep 26 & Oct 26; 1958 Jan 20); W. Pat Jennings (1956 Oct 15, 22 & Nov 9); Ambassador of Iran, Dr. Ali Amini (1956 Nov 7); Paul Mellon (1956 Nov 15); J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. (1957 Nov 11 & 13); Lewis L. Strauss (1960 Mar 23); Harry S. Truman (1961 Sep 11); Senator J.W. Bailey (1944 Sep 14); and Judge John Paul (1962 Dec 10), 1874, 1925-1962 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence re Re-election of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. to the U.S. Senate, 1952; (2 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Genealogy, [1874]-1886, n.d. (Box Box 8)
  - Photographs, ca. 1925-1961 (Box Box 9)
  - Political Papers - Miscellaneous, ca. 1925-1970 (Box Box 9)
  - Report on Study of the Organization of the State Government of Virginia, 1947 Dec 29 (Box Box 9)
  - Special Letters to Harry F. Byrd, Jr., including: Beverley Byrd (1944 Aug 11& 1945 Jul 23); Virginius Dabney (1944 Nov 1 & 17); Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. (1945 Mar 15); Justice Frank Murphy (1945 Mar 18); Howard W. Smith (1946 Oct 22); Ambassador Lewis W. Douglas (1948 Nov 18); Henry W. Anderson (1949 May 27); Dwight D. Eisenhower (1949 Jun 30 & 1959 Mar 13); Douglas Southall Freeman (1949 Jul 8); J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. (1949 Jul 26; Aug 12 & 17); Richard E. Byrd (1950 Jan 4); William M. Tuck (1950 Jan 18 & 1956 Mar 1); Justice Fred M. Vinson (1951 Jan 11); J. Edgar Hoover (1954 Dec 30); Eugene B. Syndnor, Jr. (1956 Mar 14); Mills E. Godwin, Jr. (1956 Mar 14); Edward O. McCue, Jr. (1956 Mar 14); Sidney Floyd Landreth (1956 Mar 14); W.M. Minter (1956 Mar 15); A.E.S. Stephens (1956 Mar 15); Thomas H. Blanton (1956 Mar 17); Earl A. Fitzpatrick (1956 Mar 19); Harry C. Stuart (1956 Mar 20); Stuart B. Carter (1956 Mar 21); Landon R. Wyatt (1956 Mar 21); Dowell J. Howard (1956 Mar 23); Bing Crosby (1957 Dec 3); Lewis L. Strauss (1958 Jan 7); Richard Nixon (1959 Sep 12); John F. Kennedy ([1960 ?]); and Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (undated, at the end of the folder), 1943-[1960] (Box Box 9)
  - Speeches by Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1926-1965, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Time magazine featuring Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. on the cover, 1962 (Box Box 9)
  - Winchester Junior Board of Trade, 1938-1962 (Box Box 9)
  - News clippings - copies, 1926-1963, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 10)
- Series III: Bound Volumes
  - Subseries A: Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts
    - 1) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1966 Feb 2-Oct 5
    - 2) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1967 Jan-Dec
    - 3) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1968 Jan-Dec
    - 4) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1969 Jan-Dec
    - 5) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1970 Jan-Dec
    - 6) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1971 Jan-Dec
    - 7) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1972 Jan-Oct
    - 8) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1973 Jan-Dec
    - 9) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1974 Jan-Dec
    - 10) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1975 Jan-Dec
    - 11) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1976 Jan-Dec
    - 12) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1977 Jan-Dec
    - 13) Congressional Record - Speeches and Inserts, 1978 Jan-Oct
    - 14) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1979 Jan-Dec
    - 15) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1980 Jan-Dec
    - 16) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1981 Jan-Dec
    - 17) Congressional Record- Speeches and Inserts, 1982 Jan-Dec
  - Subseries B: Speeches and Releases
    - 18) Speeches and Releases, 1965 Nov-1966 Apr
    - 19) Speeches and Releases, 1966 May-Dec
    - 20) Speeches and Releases, 1967 Jan-Dec
    - 21) Speeches and Releases, 1968 Jan-Dec
    - 22) Speeches and Releases, 1969 Jan-Dec
    - 23) Speeches and Releases, 1970 Jan-Dec
    - 24) Speeches and Releases, 1971 Jan-Dec
    - 25) Speeches and Releases, 1972 Jan-Dec
    - 26) Speeches and Releases, 1973 Jan-Dec
    - 27) Speeches and Releases, 1974 Jan-Dec
    - 28) Speeches and Releases, 1975 Jan-Dec
    - 29) Speeches and Releases, 1976 Jan-Dec
    - 30) Speeches and Releases, 1977 Jan-Dec
    - 31) Speeches and Releases, 1978 Jan-Dec
    - 32) Speeches and Releases, 1979 Jan-Dec
    - 33) Speeches and Releases, 1980 Jan-Dec
    - 34) Speeches and Releases, 1981 Jan-Dec
    - 35) Speeches and Releases, 1982 Jan-Dec
  - Subseries C: Scrapbooks
    - 36) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1966
    - 37) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1965 Nov-Dec
    - 38) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1966 Jan-Jun
    - 39) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1966 Jul-Dec
    - 40) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1967 Jan-Apr
    - 41) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1967 May-Aug
    - 42) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1967 Sep-Dec
    - 43) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1968 Jan-Jun
    - 44) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1968 Jul-Dec
    - 45) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1969 Jan-Jun
    - 46) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1969 Jul-Dec
    - 47) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1970 Jan-Jun
    - 48) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1970 Jul-Oct
    - 49) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1970 Oct-Dec
    - 50) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1971 Jan-Jun
    - 51) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1971 Jul-Dec
    - 52) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1972 Jan-Jun
    - 53) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1972 Jul-Dec
    - 54) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1973 Jan-Jun
    - 55) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1973 Jul-Dec
    - 56) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1974 Jan-Jun
    - 57) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1974 Jul-Dec
    - 58) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1975 Jan-Jun
    - 59) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1975 Jul-Dec
    - 60) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1976 Jan-Jun
    - 61) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1976 Jul-Oct 14
    - 62) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1976 Oct 15-Dec
    - 63) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1977 Jan-Jun
    - 64) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1977 Jul-Dec
    - 65) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1978 Jan-Jun
    - 66) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1978 Apr-Dec
    - 67) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1979 Jan-Mar
    - 68) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1979 Apr-Jun
    - 69) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1979 May-Oct
    - 70) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1979 Oct-Dec
    - 71) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1980 Jan-Jun
    - 72) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1980 Jul-Sep
    - 73) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1980 Oct-Dec
    - 74) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1981 Jan-Mar
    - 75) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1981 Apr-Jun
    - 76) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1981 Jul-Oct
    - 77) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1981 Nov-Dec
    - 78) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1982 Jan-Jun
    - 79) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1982 Jul-Dec
    - 80) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1983-1984
    - 81) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1985-1989
    - 82) Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1988-1995
  - Subseries D: Miscellaneous
    - 83) Scrapbook of news clippings re Splinters published by the Winchester Junior Board of Trade, ca. 1940-1945
- Ovesize
  - Senate of the United States Expressions of praise for his distinguished service to the Nation and extreme sense of loss on the death of Honorable Harry Flood Byrd, Sr. A United States Senator from the State of Virginia 1933-1965, 1966 (Box Oversize Folder)
  - oversize articles on Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. in The Washington Sunday Star, PIC The Magazine for Young Men, The Chicago Tribune, The Virginian-Pilot, and the Winchester Evening Star, 1969-1974 (Box Oversize Folder)